{"tossups": [{"question": "This man exiled a rival to Compi\u00b4egne [com-pain] after she tried to have this man dismissed in the Day of the Dupes. This rival of Marie de Medici and founder of the Academie Fran\u00b8caise engineered the siege of La Rochelle and French participation in the Thirty Years\u2019 War, and was known as the \u201cRed Eminence\u201d. For ten points, name this cardinal and chief minister to Louis XIII.", "answer": "Cardinal<b> Richelieu</b> (or Armand Jean<b> du Plessis</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man gathered a small handful of early followers at a deer park near Sarnath. During one sermon, this man was not understood by anyone except Mahakashyapa, who smiled when this man held up a white lotus. After this figure\u2019s enlightenment, he described the Eightfold Path as a method of escaping samsara and attaining nirvana. For ten points, name this religious figure whose teachings form the basis for an Asian religion.", "answer": "Siddhartha<b> Gautama</b> (or the<b> Buddha</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Japan\u2019s capture of this location led to the largest surrender of British forces in history. The British East India Company annexed this island from the Sultanate of Johor, allowing Stamford Raffles to found a trading post that has developed into the southernmost of the four \u201cAsian Tiger\u201d economies. For ten points, name this island city-state that was expelled from Malaysia in 1965.", "answer": "<b> Singapore</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A poet who fought in this war described escaping from the battle \u201cdown some profound dull tunnel\u201dinto Hell. In a novel, Albert Kropp\u2019s leg is amputated during this war. Another poem about this war describes \u201can ecstasy of fumbling/Fitting the clumsy helmets just in time\u201d and takes its title from Horace\u2019s\u201cold Lie.\u201d Wilfred Owen fought in, for ten points, what war, the setting for Erich Maria Remarque\u2019s novel <em>All Quiet on the Western Front</em>?", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> (or<b> WWI</b> or the<b> Great War</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "Daniel Dennett wrote a book titled for this man\u2019s \u201cDangerous Idea.\u201d Some of this man\u2019s work was jointly published with Alfred Russel Wallace. His work was defended by the \u201cBulldog\u201d Thomas Huxley as superior to the similar theories proposed by Lamarck. This man described his journey to the Galapagos Islands in 1839\u2019s<em> The Voyage of the Beagle</em>. For ten points, name this British scientist whose<em> On the</em> <em>Origin of Species</em> is considered the cornerstone of evolutionary biology.", "answer": "Charles<b> Darwin</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "A treaty agreed to during this man\u2019s presidency revolutionized diplomacy by requiring arbitration to settle disputes over the American-Canadian border. During this man\u2019s presidency, the popular Pinckney\u2019s Treaty with Spain and the unpopular Jay\u2019s Treaty with Great Britain were both signed. He urged the United States to resist \u201centangling\u201d alliances with Europe and avoid political parties in his farewell address. Thomas Jefferson served as the Secretary of State to, for ten points, what first U.S. President?", "answer": "George<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this war, Operations Killer and Ripper were ordered by Matthew Ridgway. Fighting over the Iron Triangle in this war took place in the Battles of Triangle Hill and Pork Chop Hill. In this war, US F-86 Sabres fought over MiG Alley and an intervention by Chinese forces over the Yalu River led to the dismissal of Douglas MacArthur. The United States led UN forces to the 38th parallel in, for ten points, what war fought over an East Asian peninsula that is now divided into North and South countries?", "answer": "<b> Korean</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This artist showed three women crying as three brothers raise their arms toward swords in one work based on Roman legend. This Neoclassicist painter later depicted Napoleon with a hand tucked in his clothes in his study at the Tuileries [too-leh-ree], and on a rearing horse crossing the Alps. The subject of one of this artist\u2019s works lies slumped over a desk in his bathtub after being stabbed by Charlotte Corday. For ten points, identify the French painter of<em> The Oath of the Horatii</em> and<em> The Death of Marat</em>.", "answer": "Jacques-Louis<b> David</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This owner of the yacht<em> Granma</em> allowed refugees to leave his country at the port city of Mariel in 1980. This man led the 26th of July Movement and declared that \u201chistory would absolve me\u201d prior to an attack on the Moncada Barracks. Fulgencio Batista was overthrown by this leader, who was targeted in the Bay of Pigs invasion. For ten points, name this long time Cuban Communist leader who was succeeded by his brother Raul.", "answer": "Fidel<b> Castro</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Many composers in this country were accused of \u201cformalism\u201d in the Zhdanov Doctrine. A composer here withdrew his Mahler-inspired Fourth Symphony after the editorial \u201cMuddle Instead of Music\u201dattacked his modernist opera<em> Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District</em>. Socialist realism was the official artistic style of, for ten points, what nation where Dmitry Shostakovich fell out of favor with the Communist Party under Joseph Stalin?", "answer": "<b> USSR</b> (or<b> Soviet Union</b> or<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b>, prompt on Russia)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man was shot by members of the Standing Rock Agency in 1890. This leader did not agree to the Treaty of Fort Laramie after fighting in Red Cloud\u2019s War. After returning from Canada and performing in <em>Buffalo Bill\u2019s Wild West</em> show, this man was killed for supporting the Ghost Dance movement. In 1876, this man fought alongside Crazy Horse at a location known as the Greasy Grass. For ten points, name this Lakota leader and victor at the Battle of Little Bighorn.", "answer": "<b> Sitting Bull</b> (or<b> Thathanjka Iyotake</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Protestants and Catholics in this country fought the Kappel Wars. The Helvetic Republic was briefly imposed on this country, whose cantons were formally united into one country in 1848. Unterwalden, Schwyz [shveetz], and Uri formed the Old Confederation of this modern country, whose other cantons include Lucerne and Zurich. For ten points, name this Alpine country, which has its capital at Bern.", "answer": "<b> Switzerland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Corona program was created to perform this action from outer space. Klaus Fuchs was a scientist who performed this action. In 1960, Gary Powers was shot down while attempting to perform this action in a U2 plane whose cameras were recovered by the Soviets. For ten points, name this type of covert action performed by the CIA against the Soviet Union during the Cold War to gain information.", "answer": "<b> spying</b> (accept<b> espionage</b> or equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The upper portion of this waterway was known as the Grand River until 1921. The Alamo Canal, built to irrigate the Imperial Valley with this river\u2019s water, failed in 1905, creating the Salton Sea. Construction of the Glen Canyon Dam created Lake Powell on this river, which often failed to flow all the way to the Gulf of California. For ten points, name this river in the western United States that flows through the Grand Canyon.", "answer": "<b> Colorado</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This war began with a failed invasion of the Danubian Principalities. One side in this war built the Great Redan and a Malakoff redoubt to defend the city of Sevastopol. This war\u2019s Battle of Balaclava included the heroism of the Thin Red Line and the disastrous Charge of the Light Brigade. Florence Nightingale served as a medic in, for ten points, what war fought between by an Anglo-French alliance over a Russian peninsula in the Black Sea?", "answer": "<b> Crimean</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Claims made about a social class in this work were later revised in its author\u2019s<em> Theories of Surplus</em> <em>Value</em>. This work introduces the concept of historical materialism. A \u201choly alliance\u201d created to \u201cexorcise this specter\u201d is the focus of the first section of this work, which concludes by calling for the \u201cworkers of the world\u201d to \u201cunite!.\u201d For ten points, name this 1848 political pamphlet co-written by Friedrich Engels and Karl Marx.", "answer": "The<b> Communist Manifesto</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man ordered the construction of the Great Man-Made River to irrigate his country and renamed his state as a</b><em><b> jamahiriya</b></em><b> as part of his Third International Theory. This man</b> <b>was accused of being behind the (+)</b> <b>Lockerbie bombing, causing his country to be listed</b> <b>as a state sponsor of terror. This man was overthrown in a 2011 revolution in which NATO enforced a no-fly zone and an (*)</b> American embassy in Benghazi was attacked. For ten points, name this longtime dictator of Libya.", "answer": "Muammar al-<b>Gaddafi</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This kingdom bought the province of Neumark from the Teutonic Order and attempted to establish hegemony with the creation of a customs union called the</b><em><b> Zollverein</b></em><b>. It</b> <b>was formed after a union of its namesake duchy, now known as (+)</b> <b>Kaliningrad, with</b> <b>Brandenburg under the Hohenzollern dynasty. This country\u2019s army was reformed by (*) </b>Frederick Wilhelm I, making it the most disciplined force in Europe. For ten points, name this kingdom, the largest of the states that founded Germany, with capital at Berlin.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Prussia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A use of this technology by the Kingdom of Mysore was refined by William Congreve. The introduction of another form of this technology allowed Hongi Hika to win inter-tribal wars among the (+) Maori on New Zealand. Ottoman Janissaries were trained in using this technology under Mehmed the Conqueror. (*) </b> Guy Fawkes\u2019s failed plot to destroy Parliament involved barrels of, for ten points, what volatile material, a mixture of saltpeter, sulfur, and charcoal whose invention in 9th century China led to the development of hand cannons and modern projectile weapons?", "answer": "<b> gunpowder</b> (accept<b> black powder</b>; accept Congreve<b> rocket</b>s; accept<b> Musket</b> War(s); accept generic terms like \u201cguns\u201d or \u201ccannons\u201d before \u201cGuy Fawkes\u201d is said)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>A monarch of this name commanded troops at the Battle of Dettingen, the last time a British king did so. Another king of this name was the last British king born outside of</b> <b>Britain. Robert (+)</b> <b>Walpole, the first prime minister of Great Britain, served under a</b> <b>monarch of this name. A ruler with this name came to power after the abdication of (*) </b>Edward VIII and was the father of Queen Elizabeth. For ten points, give this name of six British kings, the third of which opposed American independence.", "answer": "<b> George</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}